<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dystruccyon of Iherusalem by Vaspazian and Tytus</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1510</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21117</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 53:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dystruccyon of Iherusalem by Vaspazian and Tytus</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In flete strete at the sygne of the sonne by Wynkyn de Worde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1510]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon. Date of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Probably preceeds STC 14517--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A4 B8 C4 D8 E4 F8 G4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Titus, --  Emperor of Rome --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jerusalem --  Siege, 70 A.D. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> ¶ The dyſtruccyon of Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem by Vaſpazian and Tytus.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Vespasian, outside city walls, addressing Pilate and Archelaus, who are looking out from within the city walls</figDesc>
                  <p>Pylate. Archylauſ. Vaſpaſyan.</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>archers and footsoldiers besieging a city or citadel, one of them climbing a ladder to it, with tents off to the left and a cannon in the foreground</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orty yere after that our lorde Iheſu criſt was put on the croſſe in Iheruſalem Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſyan that was then Emperoure of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / of Almayne / and of all Lombardye / and had and helde Iheruralem and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee in grete ſubgeccyon. And Rome was chyef of all Spayne / and therfore he helde hym at Rome always And that ſame Emperour adoured &amp; made to adoure the Ydoles. And alſo he was the myghtyeſt of all the worlde / and had all the good of the worlde at his plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure. And he had one his ſone holy and noble the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che had to name Tytus. And that ſame ſone had gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te puyſſaunce / ſo that he had grete hope and delyte in the temporell of this worlde / &amp; byleued moche ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the Ydoles / the whiche were maynteyned by the deuylles that ſpake in them / by whom all the people loſte themſelfe. So that Iheſu cryſte that had ſuffed dethe and paſſyon for to redeme the humayne lygna<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And for to reknowlege &amp; caſte the Emperour and his folke from that erroure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were in / god gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Vaſpaſian Emperour ſuche a cancre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ete al his throte &amp; his lyppes tyll his tethe / &amp; his browes / &amp; pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his berde wherof the Emperoure and all his men had grete ſorowe. And made for to come the beſt phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycyens and furgyens that they thought were in the worlde. And the more that they handled hym the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re encreaſed his maladye / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the phyſycyens &amp; ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyens habandonned hym clene / ſaynge that nothyng myght hele hym ſaue god alonely. And the ſykeneſſe encreaſed ſo that Vaſpaſyan was al lepre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght not ſtande but laye nyght and daye in his bedde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:3"/>
            <p> ANd in that ſame tyme came a dyſcyple of Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu criſt to rome / that was called Clemens / the whiche for the malyce of the Emperour and of his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke durſt not ſpeke nor make predycacion of Iheſu criſt but yf that it were ſecretely. It happened one day that he preched of the paſſyon of Iheſu cryſt / and of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayth to ſome folkes that he had conuerted / ſo that a good knyght that was called Gay whiche was Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of the Emperour came to the ſermon. And whan he hadde herde it / he conuerted hym to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth of Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte. And anone as he departed fro the ſermon he wente vnto the Emperour / and ſawe hym moche dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fygured lyenge in his bedde. For the whiche he began for to wepe moche ſtrongly / and to make grete dole for the grete euyll that his lorde the Emperour had.</p>
            <p>THen the ſayd Gay Seneſhall ſayd vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. I byleue not that your goddes nor your puyſſaunces haue ony power to hele you. But I haue herde ſaye in the temple of Auguſt ceſar youre fader y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was in Iheruſalem a holy prophete / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iheſu cryſt / the whiche dyde many grete myracles in his lyfe. For he guaryſſhed the lepres / and ryghted the crepylles and lame / the paralytyques / and heled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> demonyacles / and rayſed the deed. And alſo he heled al the maladyes of them that came vnto hym. And the Iewes by enuye that they had vpon hym bycauſe that they ſawe hym do ſuche myracles / Iuged hym to deth and crucefyed hym on a croſſe. And Pylate your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt Iuged hym to deye on the croſſe. And alſo I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue herde ſay that he roſe vp on the thyrde daye / and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:21117:3"/> mounted vp in to heuen as kynge &amp; lorde almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And yet I haue alſo herde ſaye that who that may haue ſome thynge that hathe touched the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prophete / and that they haue theyr fayth in him that they ſhall be anone heled. Wherfore ſyr I byleue that &amp; ye myght haue ſome thynge that hathe touched the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophete / that ye ſholde be hole anone of your mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and ſekenes.</p>
            <p>SAy me ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour / knowe ye not yf this holy prophete byleueth in our goddes. Syr ſaid Gay the Seneſhall how may ye thynke that this holy prophete byleueth in your goddes. For I haue herde ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye that he is lorde of goddes / kynge and ſouerayn of all the worlde / and alſo is god almyghty that dyſcended from heuen vnto the erthe / for to take fleſſhe humayn in the vyrgin Marye. And alſo I haue herde ſay whan he wente on the erthe he had .lxxii. felawes dyſcyples y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wente with hym. And of the ſame he had .xii. that were more nerer hym than the other. And of theſe .xii. there was one that was called Iudas ſcaryot. And that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Iudas ſolde hym to the Iewes for .xxx. pens. For euen ſo ſholde it be after the ſaynge of the ſcryptures of the Iewes. And the dyſcyple repented hym &amp; retorned to the Iewes the .xxx. pens in ſaynge that he had done euyll. But the Iewes wolde neuer take them agayne / And he caſte them in to the temple of ſalamon / and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>payred and hanged hymſelf. But leue we theſe wordes ſayd the Seneſhall and ſende in to Iheruſalem to ſe and there may be founde ony thyng of the holy prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / or that hathe touched his bleſſyd body / for and yf ye may fynde ony thynge / ye ſhall be heled anone.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:4"/> ¶ How Vaſpaſyan ſente Guy his Seneſhall vnto Iheruſalem for to haue ſome thyng of our lorde Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu cryſt / and how Pylate refuſed hym the trybute.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two figures conversing: Vespasian sending Guy his Seneschal to Jerusalem (?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THen ſayd the Emperour yf it be ſo as you ſay I praye you that ye prolonge it no more / but that incontynent you go theder / and yf that ye fynde ony thynge of the holy prophete brynge it to me. And knowe that and the holy prophete hele me I ſhal ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge his deth / and dyſtroye the Iewes / ſo many that I ſhall gyue .xxx. for a penye / ryght ſo as they gaue .xxx pence for a holy prophete. And alſo I wyll that ye ſay vnto Pylate ſyth that ye goo theder / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it dyſpleaſeth
<pb facs="tcp:21117:4"/> me gretely of that / that he ſendeth me not the truage that he ought for to ſende me. The whiche he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed for to ſende my fader. And alſo he ſente it me by the ſpace of thre yere. But nowe he hathe fayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me by ſeuen yere. And yf that he quyte hym not / pardon not. Syr ſayd the Seneſhall I ſhall doo well your wyll and commaundement yf it pleaſe god. And then Gay the Seneſhall made hym redy honourably as vnto a Seneſhall apperteyned / and embaſſatour of an Emperour. Notwithſtondynge he ledde not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym many men / but alonely foure knyghtes / &amp; ſquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſomtre horſes / and pages at his wyll. And af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter toke money of the Emperour at his pleaſure / and toke leue at hym and mounted on horſbacke with his men / and wente by londe vnto the porte of Vallette / And there they put themſelfe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee / and rowed ſo moche vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee by the pleaſure of god that they arryued at the porte of Darre. And whan they were in Arre they put themſelfe vppon the lande and rode vnto the cyte of Iheruſalem. Where as they lodged them ſecretely in the hous of a good holy man / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was called Iacob the ſage fader of Mary and ſo: iourned there thre dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd whan the Seneſhall Gay and his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawes hadde ſoiourned in the ſayd hous of Iacob thre dayes withoute makynge themſelfe to be knowen what they were vnto ony body. Iacob his hoſt ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym as foloweth and ſayd. Syr me thyngeth that you are a man puyſſaunt and alſo dyſcrete and noble
<pb facs="tcp:21117:5"/> I beſeche you that ye wyll tell me of what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree you are / and what ye ſeke. For and yf ye wyll tell me I pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe you for to helpe you with all my power.</p>
               <p>THen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seneſhall Gay anſwered to Iacob his hoſte. By god hoſte you ſeme me to be a goode man / and therfore I ſhall tell it you. Knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seneſhal of the Emperour of Rome / that is my lorde and yours / and he truſteth moche in me. And knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vaſpazyan the Emperoure by whom Rome &amp; Iheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem is gouerned / is ſo taken in the vyſage with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladye / and the body ſoo euyll apparaylled with lepre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may not ſuſtayne hymſelfe / but behoueth hym to lye nyght &amp; day. And it is a ryght pyteous ſyght to ſe hym Of the whiche he and all his folke hathe greate dole / &amp; dyſpleaſure. For they can fynde noo ſurgyens that can hele hym / and gothe euer in empayryng / for the whiche fayre hooſt I am come hether. For I herde ſaye &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke at Rome of a holy prophete that was named Iheſꝰ of Nazareth that the Iewes had crucefyed in this cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / &amp; all by enuye / bycauſe that he dyde many myracles in his lyfe / at his dethe / and after his dethe. And I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſayd vnto my lorde the Emperour that &amp; he myght fynde ony thynge that had touched the body of the holy prophete / that incontynent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde haue it / he ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de anone be heled / in aſmoche as he had his truſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy prophete. So that my lorde hathe ſent me hether for to ſe yf I myght fynde ony thynge / &amp; that yf I my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte fynde ony thynge for to brynge it hym. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fayre hoſt I am come hether for that cauſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I praye you that and ye can gyue me ony cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl that ye wyll gyue it me / for ye ſhall haue grete good / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21117:5"/> grete honoure of my lorde the Emperour. And I ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re you that ye ſhal be for euer a grete lorde in his cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. And I praye you that ye hyde me nothyng. For of a trouthe I ſhall not retorne towarde my lorde tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue founde ſome thynge.</p>
               <p>SYr ſayd Iacob to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seneſhal tell me yf, it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe you yf my lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour byleue not in the holy prophete / and yf that he haue not adoured hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as god of heuen that is almyghty. And the Seneſhal tolde hym that he worſhypped the ydoles / and wyll not leue it for nothynge. And then Iacob ſayd to him Syr retorne you agayn hardyly ſyth that he byleueth not in the holy prophete the whiche ſuffred dethe and paſſyon as I dyd ſe. And alſo I ſawe hym dyſcended from the croſſe / and put in the monument of the good knyght Ioſeph of Armathye / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was his fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. And ſyth I ſawe hym whan he was aryſen frome deth to lyfe / preche to his appoſtles and ſaid. Go your wayes thorowe the worlde and preche the goſpell vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to all the worlde and to euery creature. And ſaye vnto them that who byleueth in the ſone of the vyrgyn Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye / and ſhall be baptyſed ſhal be ſaued. And who that wyll not byleue ſhal be dampned. Wherfore I tel you that and he byleue not in the holy prophete / and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp as god almyghty he may not be heled. But and he wolde byleue he ſhall be heled anone / as haue ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grete foyſon of other. Syr I tel you an exemple. The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was a lady that was called Vernyque of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre of Galylee. And that ſame lady was ſo leprous y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe durſte not fynde herſelf amonge people / yet hadde ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:21117:6"/> her fayth that the holy prophete Iheſu criſt ſholde he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le her. And whan ſhe knewe that the Iewes wold put hym on the croſſe / ſhe had ryght grete ſorowe &amp; came to the mount of Caluary where as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes put Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu cryſt on the croſſe. And ſhe ſawe there the vyrgyne Marye that behelde as they put her dere ſone on the croſſe. And there was his appoſtle that was called Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>han the euangelyſt with her. And Veronyque durſte not approche nere them / for bycauſe of her maladye / cryed and made grete ſorowe. And then whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marye ſawe her wepe ſo ſhe made her ſigne with her hande for to come vnto her. And incontynent ſhe came. And then the vyrgyn Marye toke a kerchyer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Veronyque bare vpon her heed and put it on the face of Iheſu cryſte bycauſe that he ſwette. And inconty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the ſemblaunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of Iheſu cryſt was por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trayed in the ſayd kerchyer. And the vyrgyn Marye gaue it vnto Veronyque for to hele her.</p>
               <p>HEre ſayd Gay the Seneſhal this I byleue wel But I praye you that ye wyll ſende for the ſaid woman. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe come with me vnto Rome to my lorde the Emperour. For I wote well that he wyl by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue in the holy prophete. And whan he ſhall be heled all cryſtendome ſhall be exalted by hym. And alſo he ſhall venge the dethe of the holy prophete.</p>
               <p>ANd then Iacob ſente for her by one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes / &amp; a ſquyer of Gayes. Whan ſhe was come Iacob tolde her how the Emperoure had ſente
<pb facs="tcp:21117:6"/> his Seneſhall for her / for to come and hele hym at ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of his leprehode. And he ſayd to her theſe wordes to the ende that the fayth of Iheſu cryſt were exalted And alſo he tolde her that ſhe ſholde brynge the clothe and other thynges yf ſhe hadde ony. And Veronyque ſayd to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe was well contente to go theder / for ſhe byleued that the vertue of Iheſu cryſt ſholde hele the Emperoure. And yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it myghte be done all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wolde byleue in Iheſu cryſt. And whan the Sene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhall herde her ſpeke ſo / he had ryght grete Ioye / and badde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ſholde apparayll her for to departe.</p>
               <p>THen ſayd Gay the Seneſhall I muſt ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pylate. And Iacob anſwered hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold go with hym gladly. And they twayne with theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany wente for to ſpeke with Pylate. So they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym before the temple of Salamon. Then gay the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſhall ſalued hym in ſaynge. Syr Pylate I am meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the Emperour of Rome my lorde and yours And he mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth you by me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſende hym the trybu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of ſeuen yere that you owe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And knowe that he is euyll content with you / bycauſe ye haue not ſent hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trybute euery yere as ye ſholde. Neuertheles yf ye ſende it hym by me he ſhall not be ſo euyll contente w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you / ſeynge you are ſo farre of.</p>
               <p>WHan Pylate herde Gay the Seneſhall ſpeke ſo / he made hym ryght euyl chere &amp; ſemblau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t And anſwered hym ryght proudely in mena<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge hym / &amp; ſayd to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde haue his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl
<pb facs="tcp:21117:7"/> And then an euyll man that was of his counſayll / and was his Seneſhall / the whiche was called Barraba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd before theym all. I counſayll that nothynge nor ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage he reknowlege to the Emperoure / but ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was lorde hymſelfe of Iheruſalem. For alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wolde rather haue Pylate to theyr lorde than the Emperour / or ony other. And that the Emperour kep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; were lorde of Rome and of Lombardye. And ſaid vnto Pylate that he neded not to fere of nothynge / &amp; that and the Emperour came with al his men to Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem for to make warre / he myght not lyue by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute of water / bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is noo water nere this cyte. And then Pylate helde his counſayll for good / &amp; commaunded that they ſholde ſlee Gay the Seneſhal But barrabam ſayd that it ſholde be yll done. For meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſengers ought for to haue no harme for ony thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſay / ſo that they haue it by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. And then Pylate badde hym retorne and ſaye vnto the em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour that he helde nothynge of hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Gay the Seneſhal retorned to the Emperour with Veronyſe. And how the Emperoure was heled by the vernacle.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>messenger (Guy the Seneschal?) reporting to king or emperor (Vespasian?); guards in background with spears, woman at right behind messenger</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THen came Gay the Seneſhall Ioyouſly befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the Emperour his lorde / and ſalued hym in makynge hym reuerence. And the Emperour ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ryght welcome. In demaundynge hym yf he had founde ony thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght hele hym. And Gaye ſayd vnto hym. Syr make you gladde and Ioyous &amp; yelde graces vnto god Iheſu cryſt. For I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a holy lady that hathe his fygure in a clothe / with the whiche clothe ſhe was heled alſo ſone as ſhe had tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it. the whiche lady was all leprous. And ſyr yf ye wyll byleue ſtedfaſtly in Iheſu cryſte ye ſhall be heled anone / and elles ye can neuer be heled.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperour ſayd vnto Gay his Sene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhall. I byleue well all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue ſayd / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore yf it pleaſe Iheſu cryſt for to gyue me hel the I ſhall venge his dethe. Nowe make come to me that lady / and that ſhe brynge with her the clothe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:21117:8"/> worthely as vnto it apperteyneth to be brought.</p>
               <p>SYr ſayd Gay the Seneſhall to morowe whan all your baronnye is togyder I ſhall make the lady to come before you in the preſence of them all to the ende that euery body ſe the myracle / and byleue in Iheſu cryſte. And then ye may crowne your ſone Ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus. And the Emperour ſayd that it was well ſpoken And ſayd that at the pleaſure of god be it done.</p>
               <p>AFter Gay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seneſhall retorned vnto his hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / &amp; the Emperour abode in his palays. And whan Gay was in his hous he founde Veronyque / &amp; ſayd to her. Lady my lorde the Emperour wyl that ye come before hym to morowe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornynge. But ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your prayers vnto our lorde Iheſu cryſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl ſhewe of his grete myracles on the Emperour / that it wyll pleaſe hym to guaryſſhe hym of al his maladyes to the ende that all the people byleue in hym that he is almyghty god.</p>
               <p>ANd whan the lady herde it ſhe put her in oray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon and prayed oure lorde moche ſwetely for the guaryſſhynge of the Emperoure. And euen ſo as Veronyque was in orayſon a dyſcyple of Iheſu cryſt paſſed for by the dore / and ſhe lyfte vp her eyen &amp; ſawe hym paſſe. And anone ſhe knewe hym and called hym by his name. And ſayd vnto hym. Broder Clemens our redemptour Iheſu cryſte be with you alwayes.
<pb facs="tcp:21117:9"/> And Incontynent the dyſcyple was moche meruayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and had ryght greate Ioye whan he herde he was called by his propre name / &amp; ſpeke of Iheſu cryſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of the Seneſhall. And then Veronyque ſayd to hym. Be not aferde of nothyng for I tell the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cryſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome ſhal be exalted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. And for to gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege what I am. I am the woman that was lepre in Galyle / whiche was heled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vernacle. And I am comen in to this countree for to hele the Emperour by the grace of god. Wherfore I praye you that you co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with me &amp; preche to hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy lawe and fayth of Iheſu cryſte. And then the dyſcyple dyde knowe that it was the pleaſure of Iheſu cryſt. And ſayd at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of god be it done. I praye you ſaid he tel me your name. And ſhe tolde it hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Veronyque ſhewed the Vernacle to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour / and how he was heled of his lepre.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>vernicle (image of Christ's face on St. Veronica's kerchief)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:9"/>
               <p> VHen the dyſcyple toke leue of the lady &amp; wente his waye. And whan it came on the morowe / the Emperour wolde not adoure the Ydoles / bycauſe that he had no ſtedfaſte byleue in them thrugh his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſhall. And whan it came to the houre of tyers al the barons were aſſembled where as the Emperour was in a fayre bedde. And then he made to come his Sene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhall / clemence / and Veronyque / whiche gaue the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacle to Clemens. And whan they were before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Veronyque ſalued him &amp; ſaid to hym. Syr vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſermon of this holy man that is dyſcyple of Iheſu cryſte. And after the ſermon by the pleaſure of al myghty god you ſhall be heled. Then the Emper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our made ſcylence to be made all aboute. And he mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted on a ſcaffolde &amp; preched the natyuyte &amp; paſſyon of our lorde Iheſu cryſte entyerly / &amp; how he ſhall come at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iugement to Iuge the quycke &amp; the deed Whan the ſermon was done / Veronyque and he put them in orayſon / and prayed Iheſu cryſte almyghtye that it wolde pleaſe hym to ſhewe his myracle / &amp; gode vertue. And whan they had adoured hym / they vnfol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the holy clothe ſeynge all the baronny / &amp; put it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperour / and made hym adoure it. Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynent that he had worſhypped it / he was hole &amp; ſoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſemed that he had neuer ben ſeke. Then he aroſe and wente all aboute / wherof his barons was ryght Ioyfuyll / and yelded thankes and graces vnto our lorde Iheſu cryſt / as Clemens the dyſcyple had taught them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan crowned Tytus his ſone Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:10"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Vespasian crowning his son Titus Emperor</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the graces was yelded to god / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour crowned his ſone Tytus Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Rome moche honourably. And whan it came on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morowe in the mornyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge Clemens preched to the Emperour / to Tytus his ſone &amp; to all the barons. And whan he had fynyſſhed / he yelded graces vnto god and vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour / and to all his barons / &amp; ſayd Amen.</p>
               <p>THen Clemens &amp; Gay the Seneſhal ſayd vnto the Emperour that ſith Iheſu cryſt had heled hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde baptyſe hym for his loue. For Iheſu cryſt ordeyned the baptyſme / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche no man can be ſaued / and alſo cauſe all your barons to be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed.
<pb facs="tcp:21117:10"/> ¶ Then the Emperour ſayd I am moche behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den vnto this woman that hathe trauayled ſo moche for me / and toke Veronyque by the hande and ſayd to her. Lady take of myn Empyre as moche as you wyll caſtelles or townes / excepte Rome that is chyef of my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Empyre. And Veronyque anſwered. Syr I thanke Iheſu cryſte and you alſo. I praye you that &amp; ye wyll gyue me ony thynge gyue it to Clement that is dyſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iheſu cryſt / for I haue gyuen me vnto hym. &amp; the Emperour anſwered her / lady y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche you wyll pleaſeth me. And Clement ſayd vnto the Emperoure Syr I wyll haue none other thynge of you / but that ye wyll be cryſtened and byleue in the lawe of Iheſu cryſt / that hathe done you ſo grete grace / &amp; cauſe your men to be cryſtened / for he is god almyghty.</p>
               <p>THen anſwered the Emperour / frende I wyll that thou be appoſtoll &amp; chefe of all cryſtendo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / &amp; make to preche the lawe of Iheſu cryſt thrughe all myn Empyre / &amp; who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll conuerte them it ſhall pleaſe me well. But knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wyll not baptyſe me tyll that I haue venged the dethe of Iheſu cryſt / and then I wyll be baptyſed / and al my men alſo / yf he gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue me grace for to retorne in ſaufte. Then the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our toke vp Clement / and made hym appoſtoll. And made to make a chirche of ſaynt Symeon / and an au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. And vpon the ſame auter he put the clothe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacle where as was the ſemblaunce of the face of our lorde Iheſu cryſte / and put it vpon two pyllers of fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne golde. And made for to ordeyne in the chirche fayr veſtymentes &amp; copes. And he made make many fayre
<pb facs="tcp:21117:11"/> fontes for to baptyſe all them that wolde be baptyſed And there ſaynt Clemens baptyſed Veronyque with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gynge her name. And then he preched by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes in the ſayd temple. And afterwarde there was baptyſed euery day more and more.</p>
               <p>ANd then after this the Seneſhal entred with Vaſpaſyan in to his chambre / and ſayd to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Syr I haue grete Ioye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are heled ſo wel thrugh the grace of Iheſu cryſt. Nowe ſyr I wyll tell you of Pylate your prouoſt how he ſpake to me whan I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hym your truage that he oweth you. He ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de me ryght euyl chere / in ſaynge that he wolde ſende you nothynge / nor that he knewe not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he helde ony thynge of you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Iheruſalem / nor therabout And yet I tell you that and I hadde ſpoken ony more he wolde haue made me to haue be ſlayne And whan I ſawe that I wolde not make noo longe proceſſe for the grete Ioye that I had to haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſome of that that was neceſſary to you. But wel I tolde hym from you that he ſholde yet be dyſtroyed And as I tolde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a Iewe a holy man roſe vp &amp; ſayd before all / that within an .C. yere after in Iheruſalem ſholde be ſoo grete famyne that the moder ſholde ete her chylde for hongre. And another Iewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was called Iacob ſayd alſo that for a trouthe the holy prophete ſaid with his mouthe that in ſhorte tyme ſholde come the dyſtruccy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and vengeaunce of Iheruſalem / &amp; that there ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not abyde one ſtone vpon another. And ſholde be ſo grete hongre in the cyte that the moder ſholde ete her chylde. Whan Pylate herde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was moche angrye / 
<pb facs="tcp:21117:11"/> And ſayd vnto them that and euer they ſpake of that more / he ſholde make them be hanged. Now beholde ſyr how Pylate your prouoſt is true vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan and Tytus aſſembled theyr hooſt for to go and dyſtroye the cyte of Iheruſalem.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>host armed with spears assembled outside city walls</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:12"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Emperoure herde that whiche Gay his Seneſhall tolde hym / he was moche angrye / and maunded anone tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe out his Empyre / and on the other partes that al men berynge armes / and other artyfycers to that neceſſarye / ſhold come armed and apparaylled to Rome. And incontynent all they of his empyre &amp; other came theder in fayre ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce after theyr eſtate. And theder was come kynges / du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes / erles / barons and knyghtes / &amp; dyuers other pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. And were wel ordeyned and armed for to entre in to batayll. And were well in nombre .iii. C. M. knygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / without the other folke. And the Emperoure had made to make what ſhyppes &amp; other veſſelles .xxx. M In the whiche veſſelles he and all his men put theym vpon the ſee. And then made to ſyng / crye / &amp; blowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trompettes and clarons / and mynſtrelles playe on all ſydes. And made to pulle vp the ſaylles in ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and guyſe / that it ſemed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heuen and erthe ſholde aſſemble togyder. And they had ſo good wynde and ſo fayre weder that within .v. wekes they arryued at the porte of Acre. Soo that in a mornynge at the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were within the towne of Acre came and yelded the keyes to the Emperour. And he toke them to mercy. And whan they had refreſſhed them there / Vaſpaſyan and Tytus his ſone with all theyr armye wente and aſſyeged a caſtell / that was bytwene Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem &amp; acre / and it was called Alcaffert. And whan the Iewes of the caſtell ſawe ſo many men lodged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the caſtell. They wolde haue yelded them glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yf they had knowen they ſholde haue had mercye.</p>
               <p>Whan all the hooſt was in theyr tentes our lorde ſent
<pb facs="tcp:21117:12"/> ſo grete ſnowes / and ſo grete wynde that with payne myght ony holde them in the hooſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtell was well ſtuffed and garnyſſhed of all thynges. For the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of the caſtell hadde fortefyed it / whiche was a holy man &amp; a good knight of Ioſeph of Armathies kynne that put our lorde in ſepulcre.</p>
               <p>SOne after the Emperour toke the caſtell &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to ſlee all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes ſaue Iafet &amp; .viii. other that were hydde in a ſeller vnder the erthe / &amp; were the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thre dayes. And whan they ſawe they dyed for hon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre they ete one after another / excepte Iafet and one of his coſyns y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accorded not therto. Then Iafet ſayd vnto hym. I was lorde of this caſtell / and alſo I was holden for noble and a holy man. Grete foly ſhall it be to vs yf we dye here. Yſſue we out for we may lyue no lenger / &amp; go we hardyly to the Emperour / &amp; make vs be knowen to hym / &amp; I am ſure he wyll take vs to gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and mercye.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen the Emperour made to bete downe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtell and fyll the dytches. And Iafet and his coſyn yſſued hut of the caue and went vnto the Emperour and kneled downe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hym. And Iafet ſayd vnto the emper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our. Syr I was lorde of this caſtell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue made to bete downe. And nowe I haue vnderſtonde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are comen in to this countre for to venge the dethe &amp; the paſſyon of our lorde Iheſu cryſt / that with wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge was crucefyed within the Cyte of Iheruſalem.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:13"/>
               <p> And are comen for to take Pylate / for he conſented y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayd dethe. And knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my coſyn Ioſeph of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathye dyſcended the holy prophete of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / &amp; put hym in ſepulcre. And knowe that we may do you gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te eaſe yf ye wyll take Iheruſalem / thrugh counſayll So we praye you ſyr to haue mercye on vs. And then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour toke them to mercy. And Iafet prayed them to gyue them ſome mete / in countynge them all theyr myſeryes of hongre / and the Emperour made them haue mete / &amp; demaunded theim yf they byleued in Iheſu cryſt / &amp; they ſayd ye. Then he made them of his preuy counſayll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan &amp; Tytus toke counſayll / &amp; howe they beſyeged Iheruſalem.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>monarch on throne flanked by counsellors</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:13"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd after Vaſpaſyan and Tytus his ſone had counſayll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde go before Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem with all theyr hooſt. And it happe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned them that whiche ſaynt Luke recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayd. Whan Iheſu cryſte approched nere Iheruſalem he wepte vpon it &amp; ſayd to the Cyte yf thou knewe what ſhall happen the thou wolde we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe. For thou knoweſt not the daye of thy vyſytacyon for thou ſhalte be all enuyronned / aſſyeged / and aſſayl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led. And they ſhall not leue one ſtone vpon another / &amp; the ſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be with the ſhall be dyſtroyed.</p>
               <p>PYlate knewe not yet nothynge of the comynge of the emperour / nor of his men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came agayn hym. For on ſuche a daye euery yere the Iewes of all the lande theraboute made a grete feeſt in the cyte of Iheruſalem. And alſo there was comen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gretteſt par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the Iewes. And the ſone of Herodes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned kynge of Galylee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was called Archelaus was comen to the feeſt with all his men. And whyles that the Iewes was in Iheruſalem / there belwe ſoo grete a wynde that none of the Iewes wold not yſſue out of the cyte / nor retourne to go in to theyr countres bycauſe of the wynde that was ſo grete and ſtronge.</p>
               <p>ANd then Vaſpaſyan the Emperour &amp; Tytus his ſone with all theyr hooſt came and aſſeged Iheruſalem all aboute / by ſuche maner that there ne myght nothynge yſſue nor entre but that it paſſed by the hooſt. And whan Pylate &amp; they that were within
<pb facs="tcp:21117:14"/> the cyte of Iheruſalem ſawe the hooſt and ſoo many folke aboute the towne / they were moche ſtrongely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſhed. And Pylate was then moche abaſſhed. And then the kyng Archylaus was ſore abaſſhed &amp; ſayd to Pylate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde doubte of nothynge / for there was ſo moche good chyualry in the cyte of Iheruſalem / &amp; that ſhe was ſo well and ſoo ſtrongly garnyſſhed that they neded not to fere of nothyng / ſo that they armed them and wente all aſſayll and ſende backe them that were in the hooſt of the Emperour. To the ende that they of the ſayd hooſt dyde repente theim of that they were comen. And alſo that the hooſt myght not longe endure by defaute of water. And the counſayl pleaſed moche Pylate / and made crye thrughe al the cyte that euery body ſholde arme hym. And incontynent euery body armed hym. And whan they were euerychone ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med they came before pylate at the palays. And whan they wolde haue yſſued out of the cyte of Iheruſalem the Emperours men were ſo nere approched the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the cyte that they durſt not yſſue / but had coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll to ſhytte the gates / and put a partye to kepe the walles / and the other dyſarmed theym to bere ſtones vpon the walles. And incontynente made to crye that euery man ſholde bere ſtones vpon the walles. Except them that kepte the walles / and that the cyte ſholde be well garnyſſhed. They were well .lx. thouſande to be re ſtones vpon the walles. And Pylate and the kynge Archylaus were dyfarmed / and eche of theym had on theyr mauntelles of grene / and Pylate helde a whyte ſtaffe in his hande. And Pylate and the kynge Archy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus ſente worde to the Emperour that they wolde go and ſpeke with hym vpon aſſuraunce / withoute ony
<pb facs="tcp:21117:14"/> fraude or gyle.</p>
               <p>THen Vaſpaſyan the Emperoure / Iafet / Gay the Seneſhall with .xl. knyghtes came to the walle of the cyte where as was Pylate and the kynge Archylaus. And Tytus ſone of the Emperoure abode in the hooſt. And then Vaſpaſyan demaunded of gay his Seneſhall whiche was Pylate. And he ſayd vnto hym that it was he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helde the whyte ſtaffe in his han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. Then Vaſpaſyan began for to ſpeke vnto Pylate and ſayd. Pylate my noble Iulyus ceſar gaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem in kepyng / and wylled that thou was his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoſt / and that thou gouerned this lande. And whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knewe that he was deed thou ſent me the truage that thou ought by thre yere. And ſyth haſt ben ſeuen yere without ſendynge it me. And whan I ſente to the for it by Gay my Seneſhall thou ſayd vnto hym vyllany And ſayd to hym that thou helde nothynge of me / and yet ſayd to hym that I ſholde képe well Rome &amp; Lom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bardye / &amp; that thou ſholde kepe wel Iheruſalem / and reknowledged no homage nor truage. Wherfore I wyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou make open the gates of this cyte to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may do my wyll with the &amp; with all them that is en habytynge there within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan ſpake vnto Pylate / and what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere Pylate gaue hym.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:15"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Vespasian, outside city walls, addressing Pilate and Archelaus, who are looking out from within the city walls</figDesc>
                  <p>Pylate. Archylauſ. Vaſpaſyan.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen anſwered Pylate to Vaſpaſian them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour and ſayd that he ſholde take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll / and ſo departed and wente and held hys counſayll with all his barons / and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kynge Archylaus. And the ſayd Archy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laus ſpake fyrſte and ſayd to hym that he neded not to doubte the menaces of the Emperour. For you maye wele defende you agaynſt him and reſyſte. For you ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue within this cyte ſo moche good chyualry that I by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue that in the thyrde partye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde there is not ſoo many good men. And it ſholde be greate ſhame to you yf you defended you not agaynſt the Emperoure
<pb facs="tcp:21117:15"/> And myſhappe take hym that ſhal yelde hym to them perour to do his wyll. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge Archylaus had ſpoken ſo / the Seneſhall of Pylate that was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Barrabam ſayd to Pylate. Syr the kynge gyueth you good counſayll. For knowe certaynly that ye nede not to haue fere of the Emperour / for he hathe not the puyſſaunce to abyde with his hooſt in this countree the ſpace of two monethes / for they ſhall haue no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but yf they go and fetche it ryghte ferre at the lake of the deuyll. There where as peryſſhed two cytees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that was called Sodom &amp; Gomor. And that ſholde be to grete payne for them. Wherfore I byleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour maye not abyde longe aboute vs. And alſo we may well holde vs .vii. yere agaynſte hym. Wherfore I counſayll you that you defye hym of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that he hathe ben ſo hardy to come on this ſyde the ſee. And that he retourne the ſoneſt that he may. And Pylate and the kynge Archylaus and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baronny helde it for good counſayll / and wente vpon the walle where the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour with all his men abode hym at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fote of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd walle. And Pylate began to ſpeke to the Emperoure and ſayd. Syr retourne your way and kepe wel your lande. For I ſhall kepe this cyte well from you / &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all myne enemyes. And knowe that I ſhall not yelde you this cyte. But I counſayll you that you dyſtroye you not / &amp; that you retourne.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperour ſaid to pylate. Do not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to me to retourne / but tell me yf ye wyll yel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de me the Cyte as to your ſouerayne lorde temporell. For I promyſe you that you nor no man within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:21117:16"/> ſhall haue no mercy of me. Then ſayd Pylate ye ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke folyſſhely / for knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall not yelde you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte nor reknowlege you not for lorde / but defye you from henſforth. And wyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall do with you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that ye wolde do with me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How Vaſpaſyan retourned all angrye in to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyllyons / &amp; how his knyghtes complayned vnto hym for water for theyr horſes.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>seated man (king or emperor?), at left, gesturing toward group of standing people (nobles or courtiers?) in robes, at right; off to the left side, a view of some buildings</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THen the Emperour retourned to his tentes all angrye / &amp; recounted all vnto his ſone Tytus / the whiche thanked god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was ſo happened. Then
<pb facs="tcp:21117:16"/> came there many knyghtes and pages before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour demaundynge hym how they ſholde haue wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / for .xl. myle aboute the hooſt they myght fynde no water for to water theyr horſes. Whan the Emperour herde thoſe complayntes he meruaylled / &amp; ſayd to Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fet of Caſſet. How may we haue water for our horſes and other beeſtes. And Iafet ſayd. Syr and you haue grete foyſon of beeſtes make many to be flayne &amp; ſalte the fleſſhe for the men of the hooſt / and make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hydes to be dreſſed and ſewed togyder / and make bougettes of them for to cary the water ſtyll from the lake of the deuyll in to the valeye of Ioſephat tyll that it be full / And whan the Emperour and Tytus his ſone hadde herde Iafet gyue ſuche cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll they helde it for good And anone they made to flee what oxen / what kyen / gotes / camelles / and horſes .lx. thouſande. And ſythe made to ſalte the fleſſhe / and corye the ſkynnes / and ſewe them togyder / &amp; ſtratched them in the valeye of Ioſaphat. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valeye of Ioſaphat was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraylled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour ſayd to Iafet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to make come water from the lake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll / and to fyll the valeye of Ioſaphat.</p>
               <p>IAphet made redy two thouſande horſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bare water euery daye inceſſauntly from the lake of the deuyll / and made it to be put in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valeye aforſayd as it had ben a ponde all full / ſo moche that the valey was all full / &amp; helde alſo wel as it had ben all of one pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce And by the wyl of god the water was alſo fayre and clere / and alſo freſſhe as the water that cometh out of the roche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:17"/> ¶ How Pylate and kynge Archylaus put Iacob the fader of Mary Iacobe in pryſon / &amp; how an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel had hym out of the cyte. And how he recounted it to Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſyan and Tytus.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Jacob addressing Vespasian and Titus</figDesc>
                  <p>Iacob. Vaspa. Tytus.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Pylate and the kynge Archylaus / and the other folke of Iheruſalem ſawe that the valeye of Ioſaphat was full of water / they meruaylled moche / &amp; thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght incontynent that Iafet had gyuen that counſayll. For he was a holy man Iewe and of grete engyn. And Pylate began to abaſſhe hym right ſtrongly / and in his herte thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde he were
<pb facs="tcp:21117:17"/> out of the cyte in a felde. And repented hym moche of that he had not yelded the cyte to the Emperour. And the kyng Archylaus and Barrabam the Seneſhal of Pylate that had gyuen hym that counſayll comforted hym moche ſtrongly and gretely / and ſayd vnto hym Pylate wherfore do you abaſſhe you / for yf the emper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our and all his hooſt abyde here ſeuen yere / they ſhall haue neyther ſtrength nor puyſſaunce to haue this cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te by force. And alſo he may not abyde here longe / by the whiche we ſhall acquyre grete honoure.</p>
               <p>ANd whan Iacob fader of mary Iacobe herde this he helde it for grete foly / and ſayd to Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. Syr I meruayll me moche how ye byleue this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe tell you. For wytte it certaynly that you can not holde / nor we agaynſt the Emperour. But and ye wyl byleue me I ſhall gyue you good counſayl. And Pyla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te wolde wete what counſayl he ſholde gyue. And Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cob ſayd to hym / ſyr ſende worde to the Emperoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyll yelde hym the cyte to doo his pleaſure. And I byleue he ſhall take you to mercy. And thenne Pylate ſayd vnto hym / thou art acurſed / and alſo haſt renyed our lawe. Soo thou ought not to be byleued / nor thy counſayl alſo. For yf the Emperour had this cyte thou wolde retorne and byleue in his lawe payen / and well it appereth. For thou ſente vnto hym Veronyque y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a falſe woman and a wytche / that hathe heled hym by her vnhappy craftes and enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tementes. Thou haſt done that / &amp; I ſhall take vengeaunce on the. Then Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late made hym to be taken and faſtened to a cheyne of yron / and made hym to be put in his pryſon in the don<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geon
<pb facs="tcp:21117:18"/> of a grete toure that was vnder the palays of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd cyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Iacob made his prayers vnto our lorde Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte in the pryſon.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>at left, Jacob, in prison, kneeling in prayer; at right, a city or palace</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>ANd whan Iacob was in that ſame pryſon the whiche was moche obſcure / he reclamed euer our lorde Iheſu cryſte / in ſaynge that by his pyte and ſwetnes he wolde not lette hym deye there. And whan his doughter Marye Iacobe herde tell that her fader
<pb facs="tcp:21117:18"/> was in pryſon / &amp; ſo trauaylled by Pylate / ſhe put her in orayſon and prayed god moche ſwetely in ſaynge. / Fayre lorde god Iheſu cryſte beholde how thy frende my fader is in pryſon. I praye the that thou kepe him me that his enemyes may not do hym yll. Fayre fader god that delyuered Ioſeph of Armathye from the pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Pylate delyuer my fader alſo. And incontynent as ſhe had fynyſſhed her prayer / the aungell of god de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered her fader / ſeynge all the kepers / the whiche ne myght ſtere nomore than they had ben deed / and ledde hym out of the cyte before the Emperoures tente and there lefte hym.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Iacob was at the entre of the tente of the Emperour they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were there wen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that he had ben a ſpye / &amp; began for to take hym. And whan Gay the Seneſhal ſawe hym / he knewe hym anone / &amp; ſayd that he had ben his hooſt. And in kyſſynge hym ledde hym before the Emperoure / &amp; ſayd ſyr this man was myn hooſt that enſygned me to Vexonyque.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperoure demaunded hym how he was yſſued out of the cyte / for he hadde herde ſaye that Pylate hadde made hym to be put in pryſon And Iacob ſayd vnto hym that our lorde Iheſu cryſt hadde ſente vnto hym an aungell that had delyuered hym out of pryſon and had brought hym theder. And whan the emperoure hadde herde hym he made hym greate chere / and reteyned hym of his owne courte / 
<pb facs="tcp:21117:19"/> with Iafet of Caſſet / &amp; wylled that he were of his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy counſayll / and made to make hym honour and gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te feeſt of all his men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan aſſembled his counſayl for to wyt how he myght aſſayll Iheruſalem / and how Iacob gaue hym counſayll for to make dytches aboute Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>archers and footsoldiers besieging a city or citadel, one of them climbing a ladder to it, with tents off to the left and a cannon in the foreground</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THen Vaſpaſyan the Emperour made come ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus his ſone and drewe hym a parte with Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet
<pb facs="tcp:21117:19"/> and Iacob / and had .lx. barons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were of his coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayl ſecrete / and ſayd to them. I haue made you come heder to the ende that we haue counſayll how we ſhal do with this cyte. And I wyll that Iacob ſay fyrſt his oppynyon. For god hathe done hym the grace that he hathe ſente hym his aungell for to take hym out of pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon to the ende that he tell vs of Pylate and of kynge Archylaus how they bere theym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the cyte / &amp; what they ſaye / and what they do / &amp; what is theyr entencyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>IAcob ſayd then vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour. Syr I ſhall tell you of the dede. Knowe that yonder within the cyte is but lytell vytaylles / wherfore they can not holde longe. And alſo they are moche abaſſhed / for in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande with payne is there abyden one Iewe but that they are comen vnto the feeſt yonder within. For it was a cuſtome euery yere to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feeſt And whan you had layde the ſyege none durſt yſſue out / nor alſo none toke no hede of you. Wherfore I tell you ſyr that they ſhal be ſone dyſcomfyted / for they are not garnyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed with vytaylles / neuertheles they may yſſue oute by dyuers places. So I counſayll that ye make to be made grete pyttes / to the ende that none yſſue oute w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute your lycence. And whan theyr vytaylles ſhall be ſpended they ſhal yelde them vnto you / or elles ye ſhal neuer wynne it.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperour and the barons of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll helde it for good and wel ſpoken. And in contynent the Emperour made to crye thrughe all the
<pb facs="tcp:21117:20"/> hooſt that all they whiche medled them with makyng of pyttes ſholde come vnto the Emperour / and incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynent it was done. And whan they were come before the Emperour they founde them well togyder .v. M. werkemen. Then the Emperoure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded theym for to make depe pyttes aboute the cyte of Iheruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And ſayd vnto Iafet and Iacob that they ſholde be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> admynyſtratours. And Iafet and Iacob behelde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them bothe where they ſhold begyn the forſaid dytches. So they made them be bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne where as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought beſt / and ledde with them .xx. M. archers wel garnyſſhed for to kepe them that made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pyttes. And the werke men made them in the maner that Iafet &amp; Iacob commaunded them. So they made the forſaid dytches .xxx. culdettes depe / and .xx. brode.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Pylate aſſembled his men of armes for to fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte with the Emperour.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>enthroned figure with sceptre (Pilate?) flanked by two pairs of men in armor with spears and swords</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:20"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Pylate ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they made dytches in ſuche wyſe / and that they kepte them ſo ſtrayte. He demaunded counſayl of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge Archylaus / the whiche made ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for Ioſeph of Armathye to counſayll that ſayd. Syr we may doo none other thynge / but I counſayll you that we arme vs to morowe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge euerychone / and that we go and aſſayll theym. For the ſonne ſhall ſmyte them in the faces / &amp; we ſhall dyſtroye them all. And Pylate and the kynge Archy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus helde that counſayll for good. And made crye at nyghte thrughe all the cyte that on the morowe at the poynt of the daye they ſholde be armed afore the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Salamon in a ryght fayre place that was there And whan it came on the morowe they were well ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and apparaylled / and ordeyned theyr bataylles / &amp; were well .xx. M. knyghtes / and .lx. M. ſquyers / &amp; wel lxx. M. archers and ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſurely dreſſed. And py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that they ſholde entre wyſely in to ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayll / and that none dyſordred them / but kept them at the ordenaunce of the capytaynes.</p>
               <p>THen Pylate and the kynge Archilaus toke the xx. M. knyghtes &amp; yſſued by the grete gate of the cyte. And incontynent as one of the watche of the Emperour ſawe them yſſue out all armed he mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted on horſbacke and ran &amp; recounted it vnto the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure. And then the Emperour ſente for Tytus his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and for Iafet and Iacob / and ſayd to them that in contynent they ſholde make to crye that euery Capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſholde be armed with all theyr retynewe ſurely
<pb facs="tcp:21117:21"/> And incontynent it was done / for of themſelfe it was apparaylled from daye to daye. And whan they of the hooſt knewe wherfore they were yſſued / they hadde ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght grete Ioye / and anone came all armed before the Emperour. And the Emperour ſayd vnto them that they ſholde haue batayl. And tolde vnto them how py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late came agaynſt them with his men: &amp; badde theym for to ordeyne theyr bataylles / &amp; that euery body were redy for to ſmyte vpon theyr enmyes. And whan they were redy and all armed / the Emperour / tytus his ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other kynges / dukes / erles / barons &amp; knygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and all other maner of folkes yſſued oute there as they were lodged / &amp; were men without nombre. And whan they were comen there as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hooſt of Pilate was it was aboute tyers. And the men of Pylate were not yet all yſſued out of Iheruſalem. Whan they were all out the bataylles were ordeyned / and made the myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrelles to playe and to blowe vp the trompettes / and entermedled them togyder in ſuche maner / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhold neyther haue ſene nor herde heuen nor erthe / &amp; ſmote the one vpon the other ſo myghty ſtrokes with ſperes vpon theyr ſheldes and other harneys that at the fyrſt batayll there deyed thre thouſande what of one what of other of them of Pylate. And of them of the Emper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our .viii. C. and the batayll dured vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</p>
               <p>AFter that the bataylles were ended / they put themſelfe all aſyde and reſted them. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had reſted them on bothe partyes they retourned agayne vnto the felde / and began the batayll agayne / 
<pb facs="tcp:21117:21"/> ſo ſharpely that there deyed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parte of Pylate thre thouſande and ſeuen hondred men of armes. And on the Emperours parte a thouſande and two hondred. And the batayll dured vnto the ſone ſettynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How our lorde ſhewed a grete myracle for Vaſpaſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an and his hooſt at the batayl. And how Pylates men were dyſcomfyte.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>knights on horseback charging with spears and swords, trampling broken bodies and weapons</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:22"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen our lorde Iheſu cryſt that wolde that his dethe were venged dyde a myracle / for they of the batayll wende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſonne wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue reſted / and began to departe from the felde. And the ſone by the wyll of god tourned towardes oryent / and aroſe vp as it had ben fayre mornynge / and the nyghte was paſſed / &amp; was a fayre clere daye vnto the ſone ſettynge. And thus the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was no nyght bytwene the two dayes. Whan them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour and Tytus his ſone had ſene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete myracle that god had made / they thought that it was not god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des wyl that they ſholde yet yſſue out of the felde. And then they retorned and began to ſmyte vpon the hooſt of Pylate / &amp; Pylate on theym / and the batayll dured vnto myddaye. And there deyed vpon the parte of Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late foure thouſande two hondred and fyfty And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperours ſyde a thouſande and fyfty.</p>
               <p>THen the batayles were moche ſtrongly chaffed one agaynſt another / and wente &amp; reſted them tyll euen ſonge tyme. And then they came agayne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felde and ſmote the one vpon the other / and dured tyl nyght. And there was ſlayne on Pylates partye thre thouſande &amp; .l. perſones. And of them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour iij. C. l. So that in all there deyed on Pylates parte .x. M. men. And on the Emperours .iij. M. iiij. C. And in that ſame batayll the Emperoure reyſed vp the felde / and droue Pylates hooſt vnto the gates of the cyte of Iheruſalem. And as they reculed theym they herde a man that cryed ſtyll Vaſpaſyan go in to Iheruſalem. Wherof euery body was abaſſhed / for they wende it
<pb facs="tcp:21117:22"/> had ben prophecye. And at that ſame entre was hurte Ioſeph of Armathye with a ſpere in the thyes / but he was not moche the wors. And whan Pylate &amp; the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge Archylaus were retrayed within the cyte they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ryght ſore trauayled / and had grete ſorowe for the loſſe they had receyued in the batayll. For they neuer had ſo grete ſorowe afore for nothynge nor after. And the Emperoure wente and lodged hym in his tentes / with his men / and ther they refreſſhed them / for they were ryght wery euerychone.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Emperour ſawe that Pylate yſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſued not out of the cite. He ſaid vnto Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fet and vnto Iacob that they ſholde thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to make the pyttes / to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght haue ſoner done. And they went and put to as many werkemen as was before / for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ynowe put to theyr handes. And they were wel .xv. M werkemen / ſoo that in lytell ſpace they had made the ſayd pyttes all aboute Iheruſalem / by ſuche manere that no perſone ne myght yſſue nor entre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute theyr lycence. For the ſayd pyttes were made depe and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de as ye haue herde before.</p>
               <p>WHan Pilate ſawe that no man ne myght yſſue he and the other barons of the cyte aſſembled them / and dyſcomforted them moche / and all the othe people alſo. And there cryed and ſayd euer a voyce (Vaſpaſyan go) in Iheruſalem is deed. And it wolde ſaye it by oure bleſſed lorde Iheſu cryſte. /
<pb facs="tcp:21117:23"/> but we ſhall ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this prophet was agaynſt vs. Syr Pylate ye had euyll counſayll whan ye wolde not yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this cyte vnto the Emperour our lorde. Nowe may we well ſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme approcheth that this voyce ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that abode at the gate of the cyte and ſayd. Go Vaſ paſyan in to Iheruſalem for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people deyeth now in this cyte by the ſtretes.</p>
               <p>THen Pylate herde the crye of the people / &amp; he wente and counſaylled hym with kyng Archy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laus and with his barons and other knyghtes / &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue all other Ioſeph of Armathye ſpake fyrſt and ſayd to Pylate. Syr here can be noo remedye ſaue that we make ſtyll theſe folke / and that there be made two gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te pyttes for to put them that be deed in / for they are to nere the cyte. And is ryght peryllous for peſtylence And alſo that there come no cloſynge to the cyte. And alſo that we kepe vs wyſely / and make the vytaylles to be wel kepte / for in veryte there is ryght lytel ſeyng that we are ſo many. For there is well .xxx. thouſande ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers that are comen for this feeſt. And none can put them out. Wherfore it is of neceſſyte that euericho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne kepe well theyr vytaylles.</p>
               <p>ANd whan he hadde herde the counſayll of Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeph of Armathye he ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was wel ſayd / And badde Ioſeph do it after his owne pleaſure. The whiche Ioſeph made to make two grete pyttes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in they dyde put the deed bodyes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was well in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre .xiii. thouſande. And made to kepe the vytaylles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:23"/> ¶ What grete famyne was within the cyte of Iheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem / and how the people came and complayned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Pylate.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Barrabas, Pilate, and King Archelaus</figDesc>
                  <p>Barrabam. Pylate. K. Archylaus.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that there happened ſo greate famyne within the cyte of Iheruſalem and derthe / that there abode no wylde herbe to ete that myght be had. And alſo ete the deed beeſtes were they horſes / dogges / cattes / or ony o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beeſtes. For theyr hongre was ſo grete that all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght gete was ſone gone.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:24"/>
               <p> VHen was more gretter crye in Iheruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than had be afore / for the folke deyed for hongre / &amp; whan they were deed they were borne in to the pyttes where as was the other. And in dede there was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de deed for one daye for hongre by the ſtretes thre hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty perſones / of the whiche Pylate had gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dole / moche more than he had before.</p>
               <p>THen Pylate had in his counſayll and made cry that what perſone had no mete that he ſholde take there as he myghte gete it. And of this the poore folkes had grete Ioye / and wente thrughe the ſtretes by greate hepes theder as they thoughte to fynde ony mete. And inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynent as they ſawe ſmoke / or ſmelled ony ſauour of mete in what ſomeuer hous it was they entred and who that myght take mooſt had mooſt / by ſuche manere that they ſpylte al the vytaylles in ſhort tyme / ſo that there was founde no mete within the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of Iheruſalem. And in the ende they wente vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of the cyte that were couered with boylled leder and ete therof for the grete hongre that they had. And there was in Iheruſalem ſo grete derthe that a lytell ferdynge lofe was worth .lx. peces of golde. And an ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple was worth the weyght of golde. And whan all the vytayles was eten ſoo that there was none founde no more to ſell / they gnawed the wodde and ete the erthe. And then the folkes deyed in the ſtretes for pure hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre innumerable.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:24"/>
               <p> NOw then happened that a lady that had to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Marye / the whiche had ben wyfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of Affrycke. The whiche deyed in the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte was crucefyed. That ſame lady wylled not to be maryed ony more / and ſhe had a doughter and a no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble lady that was her felowe / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was called cla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryce and ſhe had a ſone. Theſe two ladyes came in to Iheruſalem and were conuerted to the fayth of Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte / &amp; was baptyſed. And theſe two ladyes was well garnyſſhed of vytaylles ſo as it apperteyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a quene / vnto the tyme that the men of Pylate dyd ſtele it from theym. And they were euer in orayſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Iheſu cryſt / for they had ſtrongly theyr fayth And as it is ſayd before the Iewes had ſtolen theyr by taylles excepte herbes that they had in a gardyne that was within theyr hous / and of theſe herbes they lyued Whan al theyr herbes was eten the doughter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of Affryke was moche feble for hongre / and deyed without ony other ſekenes / wherof the quene had ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght grete ſorowe and wepte moche ſtrongly. And alſo the ſone of the felawe of the quene deyed for grete hon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre / for the whiche his moder made ryght grete dole / And alſo for that that they had grete hongre / alſo wel as for theyr chyldren that were deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the felawe of the quene ſawe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered theyr grete ſorowe / ſhe ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the quene. Lady leue we this ſorowe / in peas / and take we my chylde and cut a quarter / and roſte we it ſith that we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue none other thynge for to ete / and that all is gone.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:25"/>
               <p> And whan the quene herde that / of grete ſorowe &amp; hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour that ſhe hadde ſhe fell downe vnto the erthe in a ſwowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How as the two ladyes were in counſayll &amp; the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in ſwoune an aungell badde the quene roſte and ete her chylde.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Clarice (left), the queen (right), and a group of other ladies (center, smaller)</figDesc>
                  <p>Clarice</p>
                  <p>the quene.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>ANd then as the quene Marye laye ſwounyng an aungell came that toke her vp &amp; comforted her / and ſayd vnto her. Lady god ſendeth you worde by me that you ete the chylde to the ende that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:21117:25"/> he hathe ſayd ſhall be accomplyſſhed &amp; done. For Ihe ſu cryſt ſpoke it with his propre mouthe in this Cyte the daye of Palmeſondaye whan he entred mounted vpon an aſſe. And that in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> generacyon ſholde be peſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence and famyne ſo grete in Iheruſalem that the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der ſholde ete her chylde / for the grete hongre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde be in the cyte. The whiche cyte ſholde be dyſtroyed in ſuche maner that one ſtone ſholde not abyde vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / &amp; ſo grete dyſtruccyon of people. Wherfore ſayd the aungell to the lady it behoueth to be ſo done / &amp; god wyll that it ſhall be ſo accomplyſſhed. So the aungell departed from her and wente his waye.</p>
               <p>THen the ladyes abode wepyng &amp; toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde and cut of a quarter with the ſholder &amp; layde it to roſte. And in roſtynge it there yſſued oute a ryghte grete and good odoure / in ſuche wyſe that it ſmelled al aboute the ſtrete. And Pylate &amp; the kynge Archylaus wente thrughe the cyte thynkynge &amp; aduyſynge howe they myght do. And whan they were before the houſe of the quene Pylate ſmelled the good odoure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roſt / and had grete luſte to haue therof. Soo he called a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunt and ſayd to hym. Goo ſe where this roſte is / &amp; ſaye vnto hym that oweth it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſende me ſome / for I had neuer ſo grete deſyre of nothynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde nor neuer ſhall.</p>
               <p>THen the ſergeauntes that were .x. or .xij. wente thrughe the ſtrete ſerchynge where the roſte myghte be. At the laſte they came in to the hous of the Vaſ. &amp; Ty.
<pb facs="tcp:21117:26"/> good quene and called at the gate. And whan they we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re within they ſalued the ladyes and ſaid. Ladyes my lorde Pylate prayeth you that ye wyll ſende him ſome of your good roſte / for he ſayeth that neuer the dayes of his lyfe he had not ſo grete deſyre of nothynge.</p>
               <p>THen ſayd the quenes felawe / By god frendes gladly / and ſhe toke the thre quarters that we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re lefte of her chylde / and toke a knyfe &amp; ſayd to them / Lordes holde me there and I ſhall cut you ſome to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to your mayſter whiche ſhall make it be dreſſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his appetyte. And whan the ſergeauntes ſawe the chylde cut / and that the lady wolde cut it yet agayne for to ſende to Pylate / they were ſo agaſt and had ſoo grete hydour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were almooſt out of theyr wytte And retourned all confuſed before Pylate. Whan Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late ſawe them come he ſayd vnto them / from whens come you ſo abaſſhed / brynge ye me no roſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſent you fore. And the ſergeauntes ſayd vnto hym. Syr a lady hathe quartred her chylde / and hathe made to roſte a quarter that ſhe wyll ete. And whan we had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked her / ſhe toke the chylde &amp; wolde haue ſente you a quarter / and that ye ſholde make it to be roſted &amp; dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after your appetyte. The whiche whan we ſawe we had grete horrour and greate ſorowe / ſoo that we hadde almooſt ronne out of our wyttes / and we dyde yſſue out of her houſe alſo ſoone as we myghte for the grete horrour that we had to ſe her cut her owne chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and roſte it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:26"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Pylate herde the anſwere that the ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes brought hym from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ladyes of the chylde He had ryght grete hydour and doubted hym For the whiche he ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in to his palays and layde hym dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in his bedde of the grete ſorowe that he had / &amp; there he helde hym ryght dolent and dyſconforted. And the ladyes were in theyr houſe / that wepte and complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theyr chyldren. Neuertheles they began for to ete for the grete hongre that they had / for god had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded them. And euer in etynge they wept ryght ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. but it behoued that they ete therof / for god had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken it with his owne mouthe. And whan they hadde eten the chylde of Claryce they beganne for to ete the doughter of the quene / but there was the ryght greate doloure whan the quene began for to ete of her dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / for euery body that ſawe her wepe might not kepe them from wepynge of the pyte and greate ſorowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe had and demeaned.</p>
               <p>ANd whan Pylate hadde ben thre dayes in his bedde ſorowfull and dyſconforted / he roſe vp and wente vnto kynge Archylaus afore the temple of Salamon where as he was. And thether he made to come all his barons and all his counſayll / and ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theym my lordes I can not tell what counſayll we may take agaynſt this Emperour / for we are in grete dyſtreſſe by this that we haue no vytaylles / and alſo I knowe certaynly that there is happened in this cyte a ryghte grete ſclaunder and a grete myſauenture / hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryble and ryght hydeous for to here and to recounte. /
<pb facs="tcp:21117:27"/> That is that the moders ete theyr chyldren for hongre So that I counſayll that we yelde this cyte vnto the Emperour / and yf he wyl take me to mercy that he do it / for I had leuer deye alone than al the people ſholde deye. For the Emperour knoweth well that none is to blame but I alonely.</p>
               <p>WHan Archylaus and all the other barons her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the counſayll that Pylate gaue / they were ryght ſory and moche dolant and ſayd all we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge. Ha god what ſhall we do with our lorde Pilate And then the grete complayntes aroſe in the cyte ſoo that they herde them in the hooſt of the Emperour / &amp; the crye was moche grete ſeynge that it was no daye but that there deyed in the cyte .iiij. C. perſones of the grete famyne that there was.</p>
               <p>THen Pylate ſaid that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche he had ſayd he wolde perfourme. And ſayd vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chylaus that he ſholde arme hym with .v. M. knyghtes. And whan they were armed they wente to the dytche there as the Emperour was. To the which they maunded that they wolde ſpeke with hym in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uete. And incontynent the Emperour / tytus his ſone Iafet and Iacob and .xx. M. knyghtes well armed ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me where Pylate &amp; the kynge Archylaus abode them And whan the Emperour was come Pylate beganne to ſpeke to the Emperour and ſayd. Syr Emperoure haue pyte on me and on all this people yf it pleaſe you and take the cyte and the treaſoure and all that there
<pb facs="tcp:21117:27"/> is / and let vs goo in to ſtraunge landes exyled by the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the Emperour ſpake vnto Pylate &amp; the kyng Archylaus and what anſwere they had.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Vespasian, outside city walls, addressing Pilate and Archelaus, who are looking out from within the city walls</figDesc>
                  <p>Pylate. Archylauſ. Vaſpaſyan.</p>
               </figure>
               <p>THen the Emperoure anſwered to Pylate and ſayd. Yf thou wylte yelde me the cyte / thyſelfe and all them that are within for to do my pleaſure I ſhall do it gladly / and otherwyſe not / and I promyſe
<pb facs="tcp:21117:28"/> the that I ſhall haue no mercy on none within the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te no more than thou had on Iheſu cryſte.</p>
               <p>ANd then the kynge Archylaus ſayd vnto the Emperour. Syr I am ſone of kynge Herode your grete frende that was kynge of Galylee. And af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter his dethe I ſucceded the realme / Wherfore I beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che you that it wyll pleaſe you for to take me to mercy For my fader nor I dide neuer nothynge agaynſt you nor agaynſt your fader / &amp; alſo we dyde neuer conſente to the dethe of Iheſu cryſte. And ryght dere lorde my fader was ryght preuy of the courte of your fader.</p>
               <p>THen ſayd the Emperoure to the kynge Archy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus / arte thou than the ſone of Herode y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the perſecucyon of the lytel chyldren / and wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſlayne Iheſu cryſt in his enfance. The man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath no pyte nor mercy ought not to fynde no pyte nor mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy. Thy fader wolde haue ſlayne Iheſu cryſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete whan he was borne / and made to ſle all the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that he myght fynde vnder the aege of two yere / &amp; had mercy on none And made ſle in nombre .C. xliiij M. And for this cauſe I ſhall neuer haue mercy on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> and thou ſhall repare the iniquytees of thy fader.</p>
               <p>ANd whan the kinge Archylaus herde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended all in a rage / &amp; vnarmed hym. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter drewe out his ſwerde / &amp; ſayd vnto the Emperoure Neuer pleaſe it the greate god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you or man paynym
<pb facs="tcp:21117:28"/> vaunt hym of my dethe. And then he put the poynt of his ſwerde agaynſt his breſt &amp; thurſte hymſelfe a fote thorowe the body / &amp; ſo fell downe deed in to the pytte. Whan Pylate &amp; his men ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge Archylaus ſo deed / they were ryght ſorowfull &amp; retourned in to the cyte / and recounted to the people all the dede of kynge Archylaus / and the anſwer of the Emperoure. Then the men of the ſayd kynge &amp; all the other people made grete ſorowe / and rente theyr gownes / &amp; pulled theyr heere / and made ſo grete ſorowe that there was neuer none ſene ſo grete in the cyte of Iheruſalem nor in no ne other place.</p>
               <p>ON the morowe Pylate made to come Ioſeph of Armathye before hym &amp; Barrabam his Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal &amp; all the other people &amp; demaunded them cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll And alſo ſayd to them. Lordes you ſe wel that we can holde no lenger agaynſt this Emperour / and that god hath forgoten them. For neuer no cite was in ſo grete trybulacyon as this cyte is / for we haue no vytaylles but ſhall deye all for hongre / counſayll what we ſhall do nowe.</p>
               <p>THen Ioſeph of Armathye ſayd. Syr we can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not gyue you no good counſayl ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour wyll not take you to mercy. Euyll were ye cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaylled to be enemye with the Emperour / for ye maye well wete that we maye not reſyſte agaynſte hym nor holde agaynſt his puſſaunce longe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:29"/>
               <p> PYlate ſayd I knowe well what we ſhal do. In this cyte is moche greate rycheſſe of golde and ſiluer and of precyous ſtones / and the Emperour and his men weneth well to haue it / I knowe well howe they ſhall haue nothynge / and it ſhall be our profyte / We ſhall make to grynde the precyous ſtones &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther treaſour ſtampe in morters of braſſe / in ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be eten / &amp; thus we ſhall paſſe our lyfe. And whan the Emperour and his men ſhall take the cyte they ſhall not fynde the treaſoure. For alſo grete thanke ſhall we haue withoute treaſoure as with the treaſoure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Pylate made his complaynt to the barons of Iheruſalem / and how he yelded vp the cyte vnto the Emperour / whiche made Tytus entre in with .xx. M. knyghtes.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>men on horseback, one wearing a crown, approaching or entering a city (?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:29"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd whan Pylate hadde gyuen and ſayd this good counſayll / they ſayd al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was well ſpoken. And euery body wente vnto theyr houſes / and they that had golde ſyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer or precyous ſtones they dyde ſo as he had ſayd. And they that had to moche they gaue vnto them the whiche had none And of that ſame treaſour they lyued well .xxi. dayes.</p>
               <p>THen whan the treaſour was all eten / all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came before Pylate &amp; ſayd vnto hym. Syr Pylate we haue done that the whiche ye haue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylled vs of the treaſoure / but it is all ſpylte and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumed / what ſhall we do from hens forthe. And then Pylate was moche penſyfe and ſorowfull / and began for to wepe before them all and ſayd. Lordes you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue made me your mayſter / lorde / and gouernoure of you all in this cyte / but from hens forth I can not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne you. So I praye you &amp; requyre for god pardon that and euer I dyde you ony hurte that you wyl par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don it me.</p>
               <p>ANd whan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes ſawe that Pylate dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted him ſo / they began for to wepe / for they thought well that they ſholde be all dyſtroyed / &amp; there was none but that they wepte / and had ſo grete ſorowe that they myghte not anſwere neuer a worde vnto hym / but lamented moche ſtrongly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:30"/>
               <p> ANd then Pilate ſaid lordes haue we good her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and put we vs vnto the wyll of the greate god and go we yelde vs to the Emperour to doo with vs his good wyll. For it is better that we go vnto him than we ſholde let vs deye for hongre / for there is not one day with another but that there deyeth in this cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te threhondred perſones. And parauenture it ſhal co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in his mynde to take vs to mercye / or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt partye.</p>
               <p>SOne after this Pylate yſſued out of the cyte of Iheruſalem with all the people / and went vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the pyttes that the Emperour had made to make / And Tytus the ſone of the Emperour wente then on ſportynge with his knyghtes alonge the pyttes ſyde And Pylate knewe hym by his armes ſygned with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egle / and made hym ſygne with his gloue. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tytus ſawe hym he came thederwarde with his ſaid knyghtes. And Pylate began for to ſpeke vnto Titus and ſayd vnto hym. Syr Tytus newe Emperour we ſupplye you all that it pleaſe you to praye your fader that he haue mercye on vs / and alſo yourſelfe to haue pyte / and take theſe poore people vnto mercy whiche requyre you all wepynge. And take noo regarde vnto our iniquytes / but of your bounte &amp; gentylnes you ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke compaſſyon on vs.</p>
               <p>WHan Tytus the ſone of the Emperour herde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maunded it vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour his fader by two of his knyghtes. The whiche two kni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghtes
<pb facs="tcp:21117:30"/> that Tytus had ſente towarde the Emperoure recounted vnto hym all the caſe. And whan Vaſpaſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an had herde that / he ſente worde thrughe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hooſt that they ſholde come al armed before hym. And he hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe wente and armed hym with his beſt harneys / &amp; the mooſt rycheſt and wente incontynent towarde ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus with all his men of armes that he had about Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem / the whiche were without nombre.</p>
               <p>INcontynent as Tytus ſawe his fader come he made hym reuerence and ſayd vnto hym. Syr ſe here Pylate the whiche is accorded for to yelde you the cyte / ſo that it pleaſe you for to take hym to mercy and all the people that is with hym / the whiche dothe praye you for to do it wepynge. And Vaſpaſyan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure ſayd that it was not tyme / for it was by grete force.</p>
               <p>THen ſayd Vaſpaſyan vnto Pylate. Yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylte yelde me the cyte &amp; all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are within (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the) to my mercy &amp; wyll / I am redy for to do it. But I tell you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall haue alſo lytell pyte on you as you had on Iheſu cryſt / for I ſhal venge his dethe in you and vpon you.</p>
               <p>ANd whan Pylate herde that anſwer of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and all the other alſo that was there / they were moche ſorowfull and angrye &amp; made a crye moche greate in wepynge and lamentynge / &amp; knewe not what they ſholde do more but ſayd to vaſpaſyan.
<pb facs="tcp:21117:31"/> Syr take the cyte and all that you ſhall fynde therin / and vs al in lykewyſe and do your good pleaſure ther with as lorde.</p>
               <p>THen Vaſpaſyan the emperour made inconty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent to fyll the dytches y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had made to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. And anone after he ſente Tytus his ſone Iafet &amp; Iacob with .xxx. thouſande knyghtes in to the cyte / and ſayd vnto theym that they ſholde ſhytte the gates to the ende that none of the Iewes ſholde yſſue nor eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cape from theyr handes.</p>
               <p>ANd Tytus dyde anone that the whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour his fader had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded him / and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred in to the cyte with the .xxx. thouſande knyghtes / and toke Pylate and gaue hym to kepe to ten of his knyghtes / and ſayd vnto theym that they ſholde kepe hym well. And after he made to take &amp; bynde all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iewes olde and yonge of the cyte. Of the whiche ther was withouten them that were ſlayne in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayl that was done before / and without them that we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re deed for hongre thrughe the cyte .C. iij. M. And as he had done ſo he made to open the gates.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperour Vaſpaſyan &amp; all his hooſt ſommyers / charettes and all the other maner of men that watched aboute the walles of the cyte of Iheruſalem bycauſe that none of the Iewes ſholde yſſue / dyde entre in to the ſayd cyte and went al vnto
<pb facs="tcp:21117:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> the temple of Salamon. And there the Emperoure &amp; all the other yelded graces to god Iheſu cryſte of that he had gyuen them ſo good vyctory. They made gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te feeſtes and reioyſed them and helde them well at ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. And theder ye ſholde haue ſene come all manere of folkes / excepte of Iewes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And there they had vytayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ynoughe / for it was brought vnto theym frome al partes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Vaſpaſyan the Emperour and Tytus his ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne made for to ſell .xxx. Iewes for a penye.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>seated figure (monarch?), at left, addressing a standing man armed with sword and long-handled hatchet, to whose right stands an unarmed figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:32"/>
               <p> ANd whan the Emperour Vaſpaſyan ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his men helde ſo many Iewes bounde and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holden / he ſayd vnto them. Lordes ſyth that our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our Iheſu cryſte hathe done vnto vs ſo grete grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe gyuen vs vyctorye I wyll auenge his dethe as I haue promyſed hym. And wyl that theſe Iewes whiche we haue taken be ſolde. And in lyke wyſe as they bought Iheſu cryſte for .xxx. pens / ſoo wyll I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> xxx. Iewes be ſolde for a peny. And incontynente he made to crye al aboute where his men of armes were lodged that who ſomeuer wolde by ony Iewes that they ſholde come vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were ordeyned for to ſel them / &amp; that they ſholde haue xxx. Iewes for a penye as ſayd is. And the Emperoure ordeyned .xv knygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for to ſelle them vnto all comers.</p>
               <p>THen whan the cry was made there came a kny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſaid Emperoure whiche ſayd vnto hym. Syr I wolde haue a penyworth of theſe Iewes. And incontynent the Emperoure made to be delyuered to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a penyworth. Whan this ſaid knight had his .xxx. Iewes he had his ſpere in his hande and came before the ſayd Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had bought &amp; ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te one of them in to the body ſo that he fel downe deed to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Then as the knyght drewe out his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re there yſſued out of his body a grete ſtreme of golde &amp; ſyluer. Of the whiche the knyght meruayled moche And toke another Iewe and ſayd to hym. I wyl that thou tell me yf thou knowe what this is for to ſaye / &amp; in what wyſe this Iewe caſteth out blode in ſemblau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of golde and ſyluer. And then that ſame Iewe ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:21117:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> Syr yf you wyll aſſure me fro dethe I ſhal tell you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute ony faute what it is for to ſaye. And the knyght ſwore and aſſured hym of his lyfe. And then the iewe tolde hym by ordre how Pylate had made them for to ete theyr veſſell and moneye / and precyous ſtones / &amp; all the treaſour of the cyte / to the ende that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our nor his men ſholde not finde it / and that they ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de haue no Ioye of nothyng. And we haue lyued lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge therby / for we had none other mete.</p>
               <p>FOrthwith that was knowen thrugh the hooſt wherfore euery body bought of the forſayd Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes. And the Emperour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that there ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be delyuered vnto euery body that wolde bye for a penye. And whan Iafet and Iacob ſawe that all the Iewes were almooſt ſolde vnto the knyghtes. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſlewe them vp for the treaſoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had eten / they ſayd vnto the Emperour. Syr one knyght amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt the other that is for to wete amonge the Iewes / ought for to be / whiche was frende vnto Iheſu cryſt And the ſayd knyght is called Ioſeph of Armathy / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ayded for to dyſcende Iheſu cryſt of the croſſe / &amp; put him in to his ſepulcre / and Nychodemus that was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Alſo there ſholde be a lady quene and her felawe and theyr two chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The whiche quene was called Marye of Affrycke / &amp; byleued moche ſtrongly in Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu cryſt. Wherfore we praye you ſyr for to take theym to mercy / for they were neuer conſentyng to the dethe of Iheſu cryſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:33"/>
               <head>¶ How Iafet &amp; Iacob founde Ioſeph of Armathye and brought hym before Vaſpaſyan the Emperoure and Tytus his ſone / &amp; how he toke hym to mercye.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Joseph of Arimathea, the emperor Vespasian, and his son Titus</figDesc>
                  <head>Ioſeph. Vaſpa. Tytus.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>THen the emperour ſayd vnto them. Loke and make to be loked yf you can fynde them / &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke them come before me. And then Iafet and Iacob ſerched and made to ſerche al about / and they founde none but Ioſeph of Armathye. And after they wente in to the houſe of the quene / for they had had often in her houſe grete conſolacyons with her / and they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de her deed &amp; her felawe alſo. Then they retorned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour with Ioſeph of Armathye. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:33"/> Emperoure ſawe hym he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym yf it was he that dyſcended Iheſu cryſt of the croſſe / &amp; he ſayd ye / wherfore the Emperour toke hym to mercy.</p>
               <p>SO whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Iewes was not all ſolde yet / he demaunded of the knygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſolde them how many penyworthes they hadde yet for to ſelle / and they ſayd that they had well .vi. pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyworthes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour badde them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſell no mo / for he wolde kepe thoſe .vi. for to do hys pleaſure with.</p>
               <p>IN Iheruſalem was made than ſo grete ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man might go by the ſtretes in Iheruſalem but on deed bodyes / ſo grete nombre there was. And it was by the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll that Pylate ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vnto the Iewes for to ete theyr treaſour. And kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf they had not eten it they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bought theym wolde haue taken many of theym to mercy. But for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of the treaſour there was ſlayne .lxxiij. M. &amp; thre hondred and fyfty.</p>
               <p>THen whan the mortalyte of the Iewes was done the Emperour made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes to be bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walles of the cyte / and after he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to bete downe the walles ſo that there abode not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtone vpon another thrughe all the cyte / excepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of Salamon / and the toure of Syon / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was Dauyds. For god wolde not that the ſayd temple nor
<pb facs="tcp:21117:34"/> the ſayd toure were beten downe. Then was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſſhed the propre wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde ſpake on pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſondaye whan he wepte vpon the cyte of Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem in entrynge in to it.</p>
               <p>NOtwithſtondynge Tytus the ſone of the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour afore that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte was beten downe he wente in to euery place and made to take the harneys wherwith the cyte was well garnyſſhed. And alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke all the clothes of golde and other clothes of ſylke / that they myght fynde. For as for the other treaſoure the Iewes had eten it / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche they were all ſlay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / excepte the ſyxe penyworthes that the Emperour withelde / and Ioſeph of Armathy / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewe that had tolde how they had eten theyr treaſours.</p>
               <p>THen whan the Emperoure and Tytus his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne had done that / and had ſoiourned them the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and theyr men / they ſayd vnto Iafet and Iacob / &amp; Ioſeph of Armathy that they ſholde lede them there as Iheſu cryſte was put vpon the croſſe / and to flome Iordayne / and to the ſepulcre / and there as he rayſed vp Lazarus. And to all the places where Iheſu cryſt had ben and done myracles. And they anſwered that they wolde do it with a good wyll. And whan the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour and Tytus his ſone and all theyr men were vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſytynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy places / all in wepynge they yelded gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces vnto our lorde Iheſu cryſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:34"/> ¶ How the Emperoure toke ſhyppyng with all his ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye for to retorne to Rome.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>ships sailing away from city</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter this the Emperour and Tytus his ſone with theyr armye / &amp; with Pylate &amp; with the ſyxe penyworthe of Iewes toke theyr ſhyppes &amp; arryued at acres / where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre penyworths in thre ſhyppes withoute mete or drynke to goo where as it ſholde pleaſe our lorde Iheſu cryſte. And put in eche ſhyppe two penyworths of Iewes / for our lorde Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu cryſte wolde not that all the Iewes ſholde be deed / 
<pb facs="tcp:21117:35"/> but that there abode on the erthe for a perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce and memory to all the cryſtyens. And it happened ſo as god wolde that one of the ſhyppes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryued at Narbonne / the other at Bourdeaulx / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other here in Englonde. And the Iewes that were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in went that it had ben done by myracle / and that had had pyte on them. But god dyde it bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwayes there ſholde be remembraunce of his dethe and paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>THen the Emperour and his ſone Tytus made to apparayll fayre ſhyppes and grete / and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de grete prouyſyon of vytaylles / as wel of whete / wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / water &amp; other vytaylles grete foyſon. And anone they put them within the ſhippes that were fayre and grete and well aourned with Iafet / Iacob Ioſeph of Armathye and all theyr men. And god gaue them ſoo good wynde and ſo good fortune and ſo good porte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> within ten dayes they arryued at valecte. And fro va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte they wente by lande vnto Rome wel and in good helthe. And whan clement the appoſtolle knewe that the Emperoure and tytus his ſone came / he wente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them with all his clergye well aourned and in grete proceſſyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the emperour Vaſpaſian was receyued at Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / and how he was cryſtened and tytus his ſone / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theyr men.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:35"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>meeting of monarchs on horseback with their entourages</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Emperoure and Tytus his ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſawe Clement y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appoſtolle they dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of theyr horſes &amp; kiſſed Clement with ryght grete Ioye / and made grete feeſt in the cyte of Rome and thrughe al the other countrees for the loue and honour of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour / and in eſpecyall for the vengeaunce of Iheſu cryſte / and of his dethe and paſſyon that the ſayd em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and his ſone Tytus had made. And then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolle put hym for to preche euery daye the fayth of Iheſu cryſte. And the Emperoure / tytus his ſone / &amp; all theyr men herde hym gladly. And whan the appoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolle hadde preched eight dayes / he wente for to ſe the Emperour in his palays and ſayd vnto him. Syr our lorde hathe done you ſo grete grace &amp; ſo grete honour that he hathe made you to dyſcomfite and haue vycto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:21117:36"/> agaynſt your enemyes / wherfore I am comen for to praye you that the promeſſes that you haue made to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you wyll accomplyſſhe it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good herte. And what promeſſe is it ſayd the Emperour. Syr ſayd the Appoſtolle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do make you to be baptyſed. Then the Emperour anſwered I vttre it / and wyl that it be done to the pleaſure of god Iheſu cryſte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good wyll So make to make and apparayll the fonte. And then the appoſtolle departed thankynge god Iheſu cryſte ryght ioyouſly. And anone the ſayd Clement made to apparayll the fonte / and at the ende of thre dayes he baptyſed the Emperour and Tytus his ſone in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the fader / the ſone / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not theyr names. And after he baptyſed the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſhal Gay / Iafet / Iacob / Ioſeph of Armathye / and after the kynges / dukes / erles / barons / prynces / and other folkes of the Emperours and other.</p>
               <p>ANd then whan all the men of the Emperoure &amp; all the other multytude of people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was baptyſed / the other came vnto the appoſtolle and made them be baptyſed with good wyll. And cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had ryght grete Ioye / &amp; yelded graces vnto our lorde Iheſu cryſte / &amp; vnto them that were baptyſed. And whan the people ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myracles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſhewed in the baptyſyng of the ſeke and lame whiche were he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led of all maladyes in yſſuynge out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water / all the people byleued in god / and in the holy lawe and fayth of Iheſu cryſte / and bette downe all the temples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ydoles / and made chirches of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:36"/> ¶ How the Emperoure gaue lycence vnto his men of armes for to retorne in to theyr countrees.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>emperor with men of arms and some courtiers</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>THen whan that was done y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperoure gaue lycence vnto al his barons for to retorne in to theyr countrees. And euery baron had of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appoſtolle theyr byleue in wrytynge or they departed. Then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Emperour and tytus his ſone aſſembled theyr counſayl and badde them Iuge Pylate &amp; gaue them the cauſe. So they helde theyr counſayll and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour and ſayd. Syr we knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pylate hathe deſerued to deye / but your fader y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the ſtraungers ſholde dye at Vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enne. And therfore we Iuge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deye thus there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21117:37"/> ¶ How Pilate was Iuged vnto dethe and after was ſente vnto Vyenne for to haue execuſyon.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>several richly dressed men (at right) addressing a king or emperor seated on a throne (at left); on the other side of the throne, a view of some buildings</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte we ordeyne that the Iuſtycer make to be made in the myddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te pyller of foure cubettes of heyght with out the grounde. And vpon the ſayd pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler be put a polle of a fadom of heyght / ſo made that it may ſuſteyne Pilate. And that he be put on the ſayd pyller wel bounden vnto the pole vpright and all naked / and that he be oynted with hony &amp; oyle and wryten a hye ouer his heed agaynſt the ſayd pole This is Pylate that myſknewe Iheſu cryſte / and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed his ryghfull lorde the Emperoure. And that he
<pb facs="tcp:21117:37"/> haue the vyſage towarde the ſonne. And whan he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ben there vntyll nyght from tyers / let hym be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended / and cut of one of his eres. And then after put hym in pryſon / and that there be gyuen vnto hym me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and drynke ynoughe / and that he haue none yll pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may lyue .xxi. dayes in tourment As he made to lyue hymſelf &amp; the other with the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour .xxi. dayes that were in the cyte of Iheruſalem: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he and the other Iewes ete whan theyr vytaylles we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re faylled. And the ere cut be put in ſuche a place that Pylate may ſe it whan he ſhall be on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid pyller<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon the morowe that he haue wele to dyne / and that he be ledde agayne vpon the ſayd pyller well oyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / and that he be there vntyll nyght / and that he ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the other ere cut of / and that it be put with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other And that there be gyuen vnto hym alwayes mete and drynke ynoughe. And the thyrde daye that there be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken frome hym his preuy membre. The fourth daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cut of one of his handes. The .v. daye that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hande be cut of. The .vi. daye that they cut oute a thonge from his necke vnto his hande. The .vii. daye that they take as moche on the other ſyde. The .viij. daye that they make be taken from hym one of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of his fete. The .ix. day that they make to be taken of the other ſole of his fote. The .x. daye that they ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to be reyſed vp a thonge frome his membres vnto his foundement. The .xi. daye that they make to reyſe vp another thonge in the ſame place of croſſe / to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he bere the croſſe as he made Iheſu cryſte doo The .xij. daye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they make to cut of one of his armes / The .xiij. daye the other arme. The .xiiij. daye one of the ſholders. The .xv. daye the other ſholder. The .xvj
<pb facs="tcp:21117:38"/> daye that they flee his berde. The .xvii. daye that they cut of one of his fete. The .xviii. daye that they cut of the other fote. The .xix. day that they breke one of his thyes as he dyd vnto the theues that were hanged by Iheſu cryſt. The .xx. daye the other thyghe. The .xxi. daye all the body with all the membres be drawen / &amp; that they cut of his tongue / and after the heed. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they make him be quartred / and hanged on the pyller in the ſame place to the ende that there be remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. And then .x. dayes after that he be brente and put in aſſhes and caſte in to the ryuer of Roſne. And ſe he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re how we Iuge hym to euyll dethe and cruell / bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that he was traytour vnto god Iheſu cryſt / and to your owne ſelfe. And bycauſe that he hathe made ſoo moche people to deye / and made dyſtroye ſo many go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de places.</p>
               <p>WHan the Emperour herde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſenatours of Rome had Iuged hym ſo for to deye. He ſayd vnto the knyghtes that kepte hym that they ſholde lede hym vnto the prouoſt of Vyenne from hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And made to gyue them lettres ſealed for to bere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid prouoſt / with the hole ſentence. Then they departed and brought Pylate vnto the prouoſt of Vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ennne and delyuered hym to hym with the ſentence / And whan the bourgeyſes of Vyenne knewe that the knyghtes were come from the Emperour theyr lorde they made them grete chere and honoure. whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoſt of Vye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne had redde the lettres of the Emperour and the ſentence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenatours of rome / incontynent he made to make a chayre. And after made Pylate to
<pb facs="tcp:21117:38"/> be ſet in it. And therin he dyde ſytte at his eaſe / but he myght not remeue hym. And ſyth the prouóſt made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chayer and Pylate to be put in to a welle. And the cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer was tyed with grete chaynes of yron aboue / ſoo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pylate touched not the water. And there he abode vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the tyme that the pyller was redy vpon the whiche he ſholde be put. And they gaue hym alwayes mete &amp; drynke ynoughe euery day whan that he demaunded or called for it.</p>
               <p>THen after the prouoſt made to plante in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of Vyenne the pyller / and helde hym wel io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>youſly with the knyghtes that had broughte Pylate. For the ſaid Prouoſt wolde not that they ſholde retor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vntyll the tyme that the Iuſtyce were done of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. And the bourgeyſes and the other men of eſtate of the cite of Vyenne made them alwayes grete chere for the loue and honoure of the Emperour theyr ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne lorde.</p>
               <p>ANd whan the pyller was planted &amp; all ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the night before that the Iuſtyce of Pyla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſholdè be done. The prouoſt made hym to be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welle. And whan he was oute he was ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged that he had no vyſage of a man (but of a deuyll) Whan the Prouoſt ſawe that he made hym to be put in to a toure that was by the brydge of Vyenne in the ryuer of Roſne / the whiche was moche depe. In that ſame profounde toure was thre manere of ſtages or places. And the ryuer of Roſne wente rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de about it
<pb facs="tcp:21117:39"/> And in the fyrſte ſtage he made to put kepers and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geauntes. And in the ſeconde he made to put Pylate to the ende that he were better at his eaſe. And in the thyrde he made to put men of armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouoſt of Vyenne wolde haue taken py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late out of the toure for to haue made execuſyon / the toure and Pylate founded in abyſme.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two men armed with swords, wearing caps with feathers (?), leaning on a bench; partly visible seated behind and to the right of them is the back of a similarly dressed man; floral borders to right and left of illustration</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:21117:39"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han it came vnto the morowe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge / the prouoſt / the knyghtes / and dyuers other went in to the toure for to haue had Pylate to haue ſet hym on the pyller. And whan they were in the tour they ſaid vnto the kepers that kepte Pylate that they ſholde brynge hym oute. And then all the brydge and the ryuer was charged with men that wolde ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyce that they wolde do on Pylate. And at the houre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kepers wolde haue taken him for to haue brought hym in Iuſtyce / all the toure was full of deuylles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo well without as within that ſayd all with one voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Pylate is ours / pylate is ours / leue hym vs. All the toure trembled / wherof the Prouoſt and all the other that were there with hym / and the kepers alſo hadde ryght grete fere / and ryght grete horrour / and yſſued all out of the toure and mounted vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brydge. And whan they were vpon it they behelde the toure / and ſawe on the turrettes aboute the toure a grete multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of deuylles. And the toure entred with Pylate &amp; all the deuylles into the ryuer of Roſne in abyſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Prouoſt / the knyghtes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geyſes and all the other folke ſawe that they meruaylled moche ſtrongly / &amp; wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wete and ſe yf the toure were entred depe in. Soo they ſayd vnto a maryner of the ryuer that he ſholde take a bote and goo ſe yf it were depe there as the toure entred with Pilate. And the maryner wolde not bycauſe of the peryll. So they faſtened a bote with cordes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toppe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brydge
<pb facs="tcp:21117:40"/> and made it go vnto the place where the toure was en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water rored moche ſtrongly And after they had .iiii. C. fadoms of corde for to leng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the the other corde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was to ſhorte. And whan the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te was there it entred in with al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corde / ſoo that they put more therto / and tyed the ende of it vnto a veſſell of corke / &amp; lete it go ſoftly / but all entred in and neuer herde tydynges of the toure / nor of Pylate not of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge elles. And yet dare none approche nere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd place. And the pyller is yet ryght vp in Vyenne. The deuylles toke Pylate in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toure / bycauſe he ſholde not conuerte hym thrughe the cruell payne. Then whan all that was done the knyghtes toke theyr leue and ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vnto the Emperoure and recounted to hym all the dede. Whan the Emperour herde that he made Iafet Iacob and Ioſeph of Armathye to wryte the dyſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and vengeaunce of Iheruſalem / for they knewe it well. And alſo the dethe &amp; Iuſtyce of Pylate as you haue herde worde by worde.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the dyſtruccyon and vengeaunce of Iheruſalem by Vaſpaſyan Emperour of Rome.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prynted at London in Flete ſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne by Wynkyn de Worde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:40"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>armed men on horseback</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:41"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde (McKerrow 23c): "Tripartite device with the mark and initials of William Caxton in the central part. The sun over a crescent moon with stars in the upper portion, and 'Wynkyn de worde,' etc., below."</figDesc>
                  <p>W C</p>
                  <head>Wynkyn .de. Worde.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21117:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
